Finding aid for Eugene Gressman papers, 1935-1967
Bentley Historical Library
Eugene Gressman papers
1935-1967
Bentley Historical Library
Gressman, Eugene, 1917-
851417 Aa 2
1 linear foot
Law clerk to U.S. Supreme Court Justice Frank Murphy, and Washington, D.C. attorney. Diary, 1943-1944, relating to the Supreme Court, and miscellaneous notes, correspondence and newspaper clippings; also papers of Justice Murphy collected by Gressman, including notes of cabinet meetings, and of conferences and telephone calls; and correspondence, 1937-1949, between Frank Murphy and Felix Frankfurter.
The collection was donated by Judge Eugene Gressman (donor no. 1088 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Eugene Gressman was born April 18, 1917 in Lansing, Michigan. He graduated from the University of Michigan (A.B., 1938; J.D., 1940). After his admission to the Michigan Bar in 1940, Gressman worked as an attorney with the Securities and Exchange Commission in Washington, 1940-1943. From here, he became law clerk to Supreme Court Justice Frank Murphy, serving from 1943 to 1948. Following Murphy's death, Gressman worked with different Washington law firms.
As a result of his work with Frank Murphy, Gressman became a national authority on practice and procedure before the United States Supreme Court. He was both a writer and teacher on the law. He co-authored the leading lawyers guide to Supreme Court practice and procedure entitled Supreme Court Practice. He has also written articles and pamphlets on the topic, as well as on other federal constitutional and statutory issues. In addition, he has co-authored a constitutional law textbook, and authored part of a treatise on federal jurisdiction. As professor, he has taught courses in constitutional law, federal jurisdiction, professional responsibility and seminars in Supreme Court practice. He has taught some or all of these courses at the North Carolina, Seton Hall, Fordham, Michigan, Ohio State, Indiana at Indianapolis, Catholic and George Washington University law schools.
The collection consists of two kinds of materials: papers of Frank Murphy that Gressman accumulated as clerk to the Supreme Court Justice; and Gressman's own papers. The greater part of the collection are the papers of Frank Murphy, dating from 1935 to 1948, with the bulk of the files falling in the period of 1939 to 1941, when Murphy was US Attorney General and the first year of his tenure on the Supreme Court bench. Always conscious of history, Murphy made valuable notes on the cabinet meetings he attended and his meetings and conversations with various public figures. These individuals include Hugo Black, Louis Brandeis, William J. Donovan, Carter Glass, Charles E. Hughes, Cordell Hull, Joseph P. Kennedy, John L. Lewis, Sir Robert Menzies, Manuel Quezon, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Francis B. Sayre, Harlan F. Stone and Sumner Welles. Also of importance are the several files of letters exchanged between Frank Murphy and Justice Felix Frankfurter.
Gressman's own papers are much smaller, but these also relate to his association with Frank Murphy, including notes that he made preparatory to writing a proposed biography of Murphy. Gressman's diary on his time spent as Murphy clerk of the Supreme Court is dated July 1943 to April 1944.
Philippines -- History -- 1898-1946.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1933-1945.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1989.; World War, 1939-1945.; Diaries.; Black, Hugo LaFayette, 1886-1971.; Brandeis, Louis Dembitz, 1856-1941.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Donovan, William J. (William Joseph), 1883-1959.; Glass, Carter, 1858-1946.; Gressman, Eugene, 1917-2010.; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.; Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955.; Kennedy, Joseph P. (Joseph Patrick), 1888-1969.; Lewis, John Llewellyn, 1880-1969.; Menzies, Robert Gordon, Sir, 1894-1978.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Quezon, Manuel Luis, 1878-1944.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Sayre, Francis Bowes, 1885-1972.; Stone, Harlan Fiske, 1872-1946.; United States. Attorney General.; United States. Supreme Court.; Welles, Sumner, 1892-1961.; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965.
- Murphy: Philippine High Commissioner
  - Notes of the Philippine High Commissioner, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Notes of the Philippine High Commissioner, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Notes from voyage of Frank Murphy from Manila to Detroit, May 13, 1936 (Box 1)
- Murphy: Michigan Governor
  - Notes of conference between Frank Murphy and President Roosevelt, January 11, 1938 (Box 1)
- Murphy: US Attorney General, January 1939-January 1940
  - Copy of letter from Cliff Prevost concerning Murphy and the Detroit grand jury, circa September 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, September 1, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, September 4, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Robert Conway concerning Secretary Hull and German invasion of Po, September 4, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, September 7, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, September 15, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes on opening of special session of Congress, September 21, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, September 22, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of National Defense Meeting, September 26, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Judicial Conference and luncheon at Mrs. E.W. McLean, September 28, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, September 29, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of tea with FDR celebrating the 150th Anniversary of the Supreme Court, October 2, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, October 5, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, October 13, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, October 19, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, October 26, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, October 27, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, October 31, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Civil Service Meeting, November 1, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of meeting with Carter, November 3, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, November 3, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of meeting with Swiss Minister, Dr. Charles Bruggman, November 7, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of telephone conversation with President Roosevelt, November 9, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, November 10, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Langollen weekend, November 11-November 13, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of telephone conversation with President Roosevelt, November 13, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, November 16, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of conversation with President Roosevelt, November 22, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of luncheon conference with John L. Lewis, November 29, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, December 1, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of appointment with President Roosevelt, December 5, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, December 8, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of conference with President Roosevelt, December 9, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Diplomatic Reception at the White House, December 14, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes December 19, 1939, December 28, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes of Presidential press conference and conference with President Roosevelt, January 2, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Notes concerning opening of 77th Congress, January 3, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Notes concerning appointment to Supreme Court, and congratulations of Joseph P. Kennedy, January 4, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, January 5, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Cabinet Meeting, January 12, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Notes of conversation with President Roosevelt, January 17, 1940 (Box 1)
- Murphy: US Supreme Court Justice, February 1940-1949
  - Notes of Frank Murphy on Supreme Court activities, January-April 1940 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Frank Murphy, on question of free speech and other freedoms, March 31, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Notes of telephone conversation with President Roosevelt, April 2, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Notes of visit with Justice Brandeis, April 19, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Notes of conference between President Roosevelt and Frank Murphy, October 24, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Diary notes of Frank Murphy, including meetings with Joseph P. Kennedy and Sumner Welles, November-December 1940 (Box 1)
  - Diary notes of Frank Murphy, including meetings with President Roosevelt, Felix Frankfurter, R.G. Menzies, Charles Evans Hughes, and Joseph P. Kennedy, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Notes of conference between President Roosevelt and Frank Murphy, February 25, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Notes of visit with President Roosevelt, May 15, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Notes of visit with President Roosevelt, May 29, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Notes of visit with President Roosevelt, June 4, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Notes of visit with Col. William J. Donovan, June 8, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Notes of luncheon conference between President Roosevelt and Frank Murphy, June 18, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Telegram of President Roosevelt to Frank Murphy, June 26, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Notes of luncheon with President Roosevelt, July 18, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Diary notes of Frank Murphy, including meetings with President Roosevelt, Harlan Stone, Francis B. Sayre, and Manuel Quezon, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Notes on Supreme Court case concerning President's powers during war time [Ex parte Quirin], July 29, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Diary notes of Frank Murphy, including meetings with President Roosevelt and Cordell Hull, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Notes of meeting between President Roosevelt and members of the Supreme Court, October 16, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Notes 1944, 1948 of Justices Hugo Black and Wiley B. Rutledge to Frank Murphy on Supreme Court (Box 1)
- Other Frank Murphy Papers
  - Correspondence between Frank Murphy and Felix Frankfurter, 1937-1949; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Notes and autobiographical material of Frank Murphy (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous papers of Frank Murphy, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings concerning Frank Murphy (Box 1)
- Eugene Gressman papers
  - Notes of Eugene Gressman for use in a proposed biography of Frank Murphy, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Eugene Gressman, 1943-1967 (Box 1)
  - Gressman diary, July 1943-April 1944 (Box 1)